RG 061, County Government
County Government, Records of
Connecticut State Library
County government records
1792-1961
Connecticut State Library
Fairfield, Hartford, Litchfield, Middlesex, New Haven, New London, Tolland, and Windham Counties (Conn.)
53.5 cubic feet
Commissioner, Jail, Termporary Home, and Treasurer records from the eight Connecticut counties.
RG061
Multiple
Historical Note
County government began in Connecticut in 1666 with the creation of four counties: Fairfield, Hartford, New Haven, and New London for the purpose of operating courts and jails. Eventually four additional counties were formed: Windham (1726), Litchfield (1751), Middlesex (1785), and Tolland (1785). Due to the importance of town government in Connecticut, however, the counties never acquired the significance that they did in other parts of the nation.
Originally, two commissioners and their assistant handled all court matters, including maintenance of the courthouse and jail. Changes to the county courts began shortly after their formation and in 1838 legal matters were separated from business operations. Under this change, only one of the three county officials was appointed judge of the county count instead of all three, as in the past. The other two officials were given the responsibility of managing the county affairs and property. A complete separation of the county's judicial and administrative activities was made in 1841, and all three county officials, now called commissioners and appointed by the General Assembly, devoted their full time to county matters.
Administration of the jails was turned over to the sheriff in 1799, an office that antedated the establishment of the counties. Originally the General Court appointed marshals, but after the formation of the first four counties, each county court appointed its own marshal, beginning in 1687. The title was changed to sheriff in 1724 and appointment was transferred to the governor, and later to the General Assembly after the adoption of the 1818 Constitution. A constitutional amendment in 1886 made the office elective. Still, the commissioners were required to supervise management of the jail, audit its accounts, control some of the expenditures, and prescribe general regulations.
The office of Treasurer was established in 1703 to keep an account of all fines and penalties issued by the county courts. Eventually the treasurer was appointed by the commissioners and kept accounts of the county's receipts and expenditures. The commissioners also appointed a sealer of weights and measures, who had broad inspecting duties, a clerk, courthouse employees, and approved the sheriff's appointment of deputy jailers.
The powers of the counties changed over the years. When the first four counties were formed in 1666, they were permitted to issue licenses for the sale of wines and liquors. In 1838, town authorities were authorized to nominate persons as tavern keepers, although the actual granting of licenses was made by the county courts. The county commissioners received the power to issue liquor licenses in 1854. In 1872, the procedure for handling licenses changed again and the county commissioners were given sole responsibility for granting the licenses. The counties also acquired two welfare functions. In 1883, counties began to operate temporary homes for neglected and uncared-for children. Prior to this, these children were kept in town almshouses, placed with pauper families, or placed in institutions. In 1919 the counties began to administer the Widow's Aid program financed by the state to provide financial assistance to widows with dependant children under sixteen.
A number of factors contributed to the demise of county government. New state agencies took over functions performed by the counties. After the repeal of Prohibition, the state's Liquor Control Commission began to grant liquor licenses, and in 1941 the state's Aid to Dependent Children program replaced the Widows' Aid program. The trend to place children in foster homes, coupled with changes in welfare laws in 1953 and disturbances in various county temporary homes paved the way for the closing of the homes in 1955. At that time all children under county care were placed under state jurisdiction. The operation of the jails, the last remaining major function of county government, came under criticism for the age of the structures, treatment of prisoners, and administration. Calls for reforms led to the abolition of county government effective October 1, 1960.
Source:
Rosaline Levensen, County Government in Connecticut, Its History and Demise, (Storrs, Conn: Institute of Public Service, Extended and Continuing Education, University of Connecticut, 1966 ), especially chapters 5 - 8.
Scope and Content
The records of county government are arranged alphabetically by county. Within each county, four possible subseries may be found: Commissioners, Jail, Temporary Home, and Treasurer.
Commissioner records may contain bills and receipts, correspondence, minutes, personnel records, and reports. Records of particular interest are: municipal building cornerstone contents, 1892-94 from Middlesex County; records related to county wards placed in foster care, 1941-55, and the temporary home sale, 1955-60, from New Haven County; and bonds and applications for liquor licenses, 1881-95, from Tolland County.
Jail records include account books, bills and recepits, day books, journals, ledger books, prisoner board records, commitments and discharges, returns, and sheriff's logs.
Temporary Home records include admissions and discharges, bills and recepits, records of children, and records of visitors.
Treasurer records include bills and receipts, bonds, and cancelled checks.
The records of the County Courts are part of Record Group 003 and are not included here.
Arrangement
Series 1. Fairfield County (1942-1960) includes records of the Commissioners and the Temporary Home.
Series 2. Hartford County (1792-1959) includes records of the Commissioners, the Jail, and the Temporary Home.
Series 3. Litchfield County (1895-1960) includes records of the Jail.
Series 4. Middlesex County (1790-1960) includes records of the Commissioners and the the Jail.
Series 5. New Haven County (1892-1961) includes records of the Commissioners and the Temporary Home.
Series 6. New London County (1841-1960) includes records of the Commissioners and the Jail.
Series 7. Tolland County (1795-1939) includes records of the Commissioners and the Treasurer.
Series 8. Windham County (1874-1955) includes records of the Commissioners, the Jail, the Temporary Home, and the Treasurer.
Related Material
Related materials can be found in other record groups. Beginning in 1886 county commissioners were required to issue reports relating to the debts, receipts, and expenditures for each county. From 1886 to 1937, these reports, known as the Returns of County Commissioners, had to be made to the Secretary of State, and might be found in Record Group 006. After 1937, the reports were submitted to the State Commissioner of Welfare and then to both the Welfare and Tax Commissioners. These might be found in Record Group 019. The records of the Department of Education, Record Group 010, contains Temporary Home records, 1913-1915 consisting of 2 volumes of report forms concerning orphans' placements and their school attendance. Finally, the records of the Judicial Department, Record Group 003, may contain items related to the counties.
Index Terms
Subjects:
County government--Connecticut; Jails--Connecticut--Hartford County; Jails--Connecticut--Litchfield County; Jails--Connecticut--Middlesex County; Jails--Connecticut--New London County; Jails--Connecticut--Windham County; Children--Institutional care--Connecticut--Fairfield County; Children--Institutional care--Connecticut--New Haven County; Children--Institutional care--Connecticut--Windham County
Places:
Fairfield County (Conn.); Hartford County (Conn.); Litchfield County (Conn.); Middlsex County (Conn.); New Haven County (Conn.); New London County (Conn.); Tolland County (Conn.); Windham County (Conn.)
Occupations:
County officials and employees
Document Types:
Administrative records; Correspondence; Financial records; Minutes; Personnel records
Restrictions on Access
Some of the County Government records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
After the abolition of county government effective October 1, 1960, various units of state and town government took over many of the functions performed at the county level. The Budget Division of the Department of Finance and Control liquidated any records not taken over by successor agencies and turned many records over to the State Library in 1961. Unfortunately, a large quantity of material was approved for destruction. A list of materials destroyed at that time is available in the Archives office.
Under administrative and professional practices at that time, the State Library catalogued much of the materials and placed them in the manuscript collection. Materials received by the State Archives after 1961 became part of Record Group 061.
Container List
- Series 1. Fairfield County, 1942-1960
  Separated material
  Manuscript Collection 974.51 F15.
  Remonstrance against removal of county buildings from Danbury to Bridgeport, 1867. 1 document.
  Manuscript Collection 974.51 F15co.
  Commissioners, Child welfare check register, 1953-1955, 1 volume; Daybook, 1881-1887. 1 volume; New Haven & Fairfield County Joint Bridge Account Book, 1895-1920, 1 volume.
  Temporary Home, Child welfare accounts, 1931-1944, 2 boxes; Detail of board, 1944-1955, 1 box; Temporary Home, Ledger book, 1896-1936, 1 volume.
  - Commissioners, 1942-1960; T002729; 2.75 cubic feet
    - Personnel records
      - Payroll, 1956-1960 (Box 1)
      - Severance pay, 1960 (Box 1)
      - Social Security, 1956-1960 (Box 1)
      - Tax returns, 1942-1959 (Box 1)
      - Time returns (Box 1)
        - 1956-1959 (Box 1)
        - 1960 (Box 2)
      - Wage earner records (Box 2)
        - 1952-1954 (Box 2)
        - 1955-1956, 1958 (Box 3)
        - 1955-1956 (Box 4)
      - Withholding statements (W-2), Withholding exemption certificates (W-4), and Connnecticut medical service cards, 1942-1960 (Box 5)
      - Yearly earnings records, 1943-1949 (Box 6)
  - Temporary Home, 1943-1955; T002729; 0.25 cubic feet
    - Expense accounts, 1943-1947 (Box 7)
    - Savings account cards, 1954-1955 (Box 7)
- Series 2. Hartford County, 1792-1959
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 fH25tr.
  Treasurer, Account books, 1873-1893, 2 volumes.
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 H25co r.
  Commissioners, Orders for Highways, Bridges, Telegraph, Telephone & Electric Poles, 1891-1892, 1 volume; Court House ledger book, 1882-1885, 1 volume; Data related to the Hurricane of 1938, 1 folder.
  Temporary Home, Account book, 1891-1923, 1 volume; Admissions and discharges, 1883-1933, 5 volumes; Journal, 1883-1887, 1 volume; Record book, 1891-1906, 1 volume.
  - Commissioners, 1925-1959; T002730; 2.5 cubic feet
    - Bills and receipts
      - 1955 (Box 1)
      - 1958 January-June (Box 2)
      - 1958 July-September (Box 3)
    - Personnel records (Box 3)
      - Employee lists, 1945, undated (Box 3)
      - Payroll, 1954-1958 (Box 3)
      - Retirement fund (Box 3)
        - History cards, 1946-1954 (Box 3)
        - Payroll, 1953-1955 (Box 4)
        - Payroll changes, 1946-1950 (Box 4)
        - Refunds, 1947-1954 (Box 4)
        - Resolutions, 1945 (Box 4)
        - Subscriptions, 1946 (Box 4)
      - Salary approvals, 1925-1953 (Box 4)
      - Social Security, 1945-1954 (Box 4)
      - Tax returns, 1943-1951 (Box 4)
      - Wage earner records, 1956-1959 (Box 5)
      - Yearly earning records, 1955-1959 (Box 5)
    - Physical inventories, Jail, 1959, undated (Box 5)
  - Jail, 1792-1902; T002730; 3.5 cubic feet
    - Commitment warrants
      - 1792, 1817-1830 (Box 6)
      - 1831-1832 (Box 7)
      - 1833-1834 (Box 8)
      - 1835-1839 (Box 9)
      - 1840-1858 (Box 10)
      - 1860-1873 (Box 11)
      - 1901-1902 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, 1870, undated (Box 12)
  - Temporary Home, 1883-1934; 2004-020; 2.5 cubic feet (8 volumes)
    - Records of children, 1883-1934; 8 volumes
- Series 3. Litchfield County, 1895-1960
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 L71P.
  "220 piecies", 1 box.
  Commissioners, Agreements, 1851-1854.
  Treasurer, Bills and recipts, 1843-1857; Leases, 1843-1853.
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 L71tr.
  Treasurer, Acount book, 1830-1852, 1 volume. (Also contains Building Committee Accounts, 1811 .); Day book, 1784-1830, 1 volume; Ledger book, 1755-1792, 1 volume; Record and account book, 1752-1755, 1 volume.
  - Jail, 1895-1960; 3 cubic feet
    - T002738, 0.25 cubic feet
      - Board of prisoners, 1960, undated (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1)
      - Physical inventories, 1942-1959 (Box 1)
      - Reports, 1944 (Box 1)
      - Commitments and discharges, 1895-1926; 1 volume
      - Prisoner board records, 1918-1935; 1 volume
    - T002739, 2.5 cubic feet
      - Day books, 1926-1944; 12 volumes
      - Commitments and discharges, 1951-1963; 2 volumes
    - 1983-025, 0.25 cubic feet
      - Sherriff's log books, 1928-1932; 5 volumes
  - A Statistical Acocunt of Several Towns in the County of Litchfield, 1810; 1993-068; 1 volume
- Series 4. Middlesex County, 1790-1960
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 M58co r.
  Commissioners, Correspondence, 1893-1896, 3 boxes; Letter book, 1893-1896, 1 volume.
  Temporary Home, Petitions for committment to county care, 1903-1955, 2 boxes; Record book, 1910-1912, 1 volume; Records of children, 1883-1955, 3 volumes.
  Treasurer, Account book, 1829-1887, 2 volumes; Day book, 1887-1905, 1 volume.
  - Commissioners, 1892-1960; T002731; 1.5 cubic feet
    - Audit report, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Municipal Building cornerstone, 1892-1894, 1948, undated (Box 1)
    - Personnel records (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1908-1960 (Box 2)
      - Employee records, 1952-1960 (Box 2)
      - Municipal Building Board of Control Payments, 1956-1959 (Box 2)
      - Payroll, 1960 (Box 2)
      - Payroll employee Cards, 1943-1951 (Box 2)
      - Quarterly wage reports, 1951-1957 (Box 2)
      - Salary approvals, 1893-1960 (Box 3)
      - Social Security, 1950-1960 (Box 3)
      - Tax guide, 1960 (Box 3)
      - Tax returns, 1939-1960 (Box 3)
      - Temporary Home, 1911-1958 (Box 3)
  - Jail, 1790; T002731
    - Committment warrants, 1790; 1 folder (Box 3)
- Series 5. New Haven County, 1892-1961
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 N42co.
  Commissioners, Account book, 1899-1910, 1 volume.
  Temporary Home, Admissions and discharges, 1937-1945, 2 volumes; Ledger book, 1895-1896, 1 volume.
  Treasurer, Account book, 1750-1904, 2 volumes; Tax record book, 1895-1928, 1 volume.
  - Commissioners, 1919-1961; 12.75 cubic feet
    - T002732, 3.25 cubic feet
      - County wards, 1941-1955 (Box 1)
      - Hospital committments, 1956 (Box 2)
      - Personnel records (Box 2)
        - Medical plan invoices, 1951-1955 (Box 2)
        - Payroll accounts, 1954-1960 (Box 3)
        - Payroll check registers, 1958-1959 (Box 4)
        - Retirement fund contributions, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
        - Retirement fund enrollments, 1946 (Box 4)
        - Salary approvals, 1919, 1936-1955 (Box 4)
        - Tax returns, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
        - W-2 Lists, 1944-1949 (Box 4)
        - Withholding exemption certificates (W-4) (Box 4)
          - 1943-1944 (Box 4)
          - 1944-1958 (Box 5)
        - Payroll, Jail, 1955-1958 (Box 6)
    - T002734, 8 cubic feet
      - Personnel records
        - Employee earning cards
          - 1943-1946 (Box 7)
          - 1947-1949 (Box 8)
          - 1950-1951 (Box 9)
          - 1952-1953 (Box 10)
          - 1954-1955 (Box 11)
          - 1956-1957 (Box 12)
          - 1958-1960 (Box 13)
        - Payroll
          - 1950-1952 (Box 14)
          - 1953-1955 (Box 15)
          - 1956-1958 (Box 16)
          - 1959-1960 (Box 17)
        - Payroll analysis sheets
          - 1948-1951 (Box 18)
          - 1951-1954 (Box 19)
          - 1954-1957 (Box 20)
          - 1957-1960 (Box 21)
    - 2001-027, 1.5 cubic feet
      - Annual Report of County of New Haven, 1958 (Box 22)
      - Calls to county meetings, 1958-1960 (Box 22)
      - Correspondence, 1951-1960 (Box 22)
      - Correspondence, Jail, 1958-1960 (Box 22)
      - Decisions of county meeting, 1959 (Box 22)
      - Financial statements, 1958-1959 (Box 22)
      - Legal case records, 1958-1961 (Box 22)
      - Minutes (Box 22)
        - 1958 (Box 22)
        - 1959-1960 (Box 23)
      - Minutes, Budget hearing, 1955 (Box 23)
      - Minutes, County meeting (Box 23)
        - 1955, 1959 (Box 23)
        - 1960 (Box 24)
      - Minutes, Temporary Home Board, 1954 (Box 24)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1956-1959, undated (Box 24)
      - Report of Treasurer, New Haven County Law Library Association, 1958 (Box 24)
      - Temporary Home Sale (Box 24)
        - Building exits code, 1957 (Box 24)
        - Closing documents, 1958-1960, undated (Box 24)
        - Correspondence, 1955-1960 (Box 24)
        - Legislative acts, 1959 (Box 24)
        - Marketing brochures, undated (Box 24)
        - Minutes, undated (Box 24)
        - Purchase agreement, 1960 (Box 24)
        - Purchase offers, 1959-1960 (Box 24)
        - Valuations, 1955-1959 (Box 24)
  - Temporary Home, 1892-1955; 1986-013; 7.75 cubic feet
    - Admissions and discharges, 1884-1899; 26 volumes
    - Lists of children boarding, 1892-1923; 4 volumes
    - Records of children, 1892-1955; 11 volumes
- Series 6. New London County, 1841-1960
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 N44co.
  Commissioners, Correspondence, 1901-1908, 2 boxes.
  Temporary Home, Admissions and discharges, 1883-1892, 1 volume; Children's expense record book, 1953-1955, 2 volumes.
  Treasurer, Records of children, 1883-1933, 4 volumes; Records of child placements, 1884-1932, 3 volumes.
  - Commissioners, 1841-1960; 2.5 cubic feet
    - T002743, 1 cubic foot
      - Equipment catalogs, 1957, undated (Box 1)
      - Expenses paid, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
      - Jail construction, 1948-1958 (Box 1)
      - Personnel records including correspondence, 1960 (Box 1)
      - Lists, 1960, undated (Box 1)
      - Payroll, 1956-1958 (Box 1)
      - Physical inventories, 1960 (Box 1)
      - Taxes on towns, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
      - Truck bids, 1956 (Box 1)
      - Cash book, 1956-1960 (Box 2)
    - T002735
      - Record book, 1841-1873 (Box 2)
    - No accession number, 1.5 cubic feet
      - Expenses, 1955-1958 (Box 3)
      - Expenses, Temporary Home, 1954-1956 (Box 3)
      - Newspaper clippings, Temporary Home sale, 1956 (Box 3)
    - 2002-098, .25 cubic feet
      - Admission to the bar, Edwin W. Higgins, 1897 September 24 (Box 1)
      - Bonds, 1928-1956 (Box 1)
      - Executions on Compensation Commission awards, 1949-1961 (Box 1)
      - Grievance Committee matters, 1925-1949 (Box 1)
      - Legislators' meetings, 1943-1952 (Box 1)
      - New London county Law Library Association accounts and reports, 1942-1958 (Box 1)
      - Resignations, discharges, and leaves of absence, 1915-1968 (Box 1)
      - Statements of William Lewis as county investigator, 1924-1925 (Box 1)
  - Jail, 1845-1884; T002736; 2.75 cubic feet
    - Account books, 1865-1881; 2 volumes
    - Day books, 1861-1881; 2 volumes
    - Journal, 1875-1878; 1 volume
    - Ledger book, 1875-1878; 1 volume
    - Record books, 1845-1878; 3 volumes
    - Returns, 1862-1881; 3 volumes
- Series 7. Tolland County, 1795-1939
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 T57.
  Specifications for Court House building, 1836, 1 document.
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 T58to r.
  Temporary Home, Record book, 1884-1891, 1 volume.
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 T58tr r.
  Treasurer, Check books, 1885-1894, 3 volumes.
  - Commissioners, 1878-1917; T002733; 1.5 cubic feet
    - Certificates of inspection, 1896-1897 (Box 1)
    - Contracts, 1878-1898 (Box 1)
    - Insurance policies, 1879-1885 (Box 1)
    - License bonds and applications (Box 1)
      - 1881-1887 (Box 1)
      - 1888-1891 (Box 2)
      - 1892-1895, undated (Box 3)
      - 1907-1916 (Box 3)
    - Minutes of Senators and Representatives, 1909-1917 (Box 3)
    - Physical inventories, 1885, 1891 (Box 3)
  - Treasurer, 1795-1939; T002733; 7 cubic feet
    - Bills and receipts
      - 1795-1796, 1822-1874 (Box 4)
      - 1875-1880 (Box 5)
      - 1881-1888 (Box 6)
      - 1889-1890 (Box 7)
      - 1891-1892 (Box 8)
      - 1893-1894 (Box 9)
      - 1895-1896, 1908, 1913-1918 (Box 10)
    - Bills and receipts, Court
      - 1814-1832 (Box 11)
      - 1833-1851 (Box 12)
    - Bills and receipts, Temporary Home
      - 1884-1890 (Box 13)
      - 1891-1894 (Box 14)
    - Blank account forms, undated (Box 15)
    - Bonds of bank directors, 1828 (Box 15)
    - Bonds of conservators, 1821-1829 (Box 15)
    - Bonds of jailers, 1887-1911 (Box 15)
    - Bond of law library association treasurer, 1892 (Box 15)
    - Check books, 1881, 1884-1885 (Box 15)
    - Insurance policies, 1830-1835 (Box 15)
    - List of names, undated (Box 15)
    - Notes, 1805-1828 (Box 15)
    - Pension claim, 1901 (Box 15)
    - Reports of commissioners, 1878-1883 (Box 15)
    - Returns for jail, 1871-1917 (Box 15)
    - Salary payments to commissioners, 1902-1903 (Box 16)
    - Statement of undertaker, 1895 (Box 16)
    - Taxes on towns, 1820-1939 (Box 16)
    - Warrantee deeds, 1887, 1895, 1899 (Box 16)
    - Cancelled checks, 1885-1897, 1903 (Box 17)
    - Cancelled checks, Temporary Home, 1892-1906 (Box 18)
- Series 8. Windham County, 1874-1955
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 W72co.
  Commissioners, Expenses of children in foster homes, 1930-1932, 1 volume.
  Jail, Visitor book, 1897-1904, 1 volume.
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 W72t.
  Tax assessment list of all dwelling houses not exceeding two acres, 1798, 1 document.
  Manuscript Collection 974.61 W72tr.
  Treasurer, Account book, 1771-1823, 1 volume.
  - Commissioners, 1896; T002744
    - Good road orders, 1896; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Jail, 1874-1898; T002744; 1.25 cubic feet
    - Bills and receipts
      - 1895-1896 (Box 1)
      - 1897-1898, undated (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1895, 1897 (Box 3)
    - Discharges, 1876-1893, undated (Box 3)
    - Notes of prisoners, 1874-1894, undated (Box 3)
    - Prisoner correspondence, 1898 (Box 3)
    - Prisoner writings, 1898 (Box 3)
    - Telephone service contract, 1897 (Box 3)
  - Temporary Home, 1883-1955
    - T002742, 1.25 cubic feet
      - Records of children, 1883-1919; 2 volumes
      - Records of visitors, 1891-1955; 1 volume
    - T002744, 0.5 cubic feet
      - Bills and receipts, 1895-1897 (Box 4)
      - Physical inventory, 1894 (Box 4)
    - 2011-121, .25 cubic feet
      - Card file, circa 1937-1955 (Box 1)
        Arranged first into 3 groups and therein alphabetically: Boarding children, circa 1937-1939; wage homes, circa 1937-1939; self boarding homes, circa 1948-1955.
  - Treasurer, 1914-1943
    - T002740
      - Receipts and expenditures, 1914-1943; 1 volume
    - T002744, 0.5 cubic feet
      - Cancelled checks, 1893-1898 (Box 5)